我的主人布兰顿想今晚邀请你来 好吗
My Lord Brandon ask that you attend this evening,so will you?
潘宁顿
Pennington!
索思韦尔兄弟
ah,the Southwells!
你主人波林怎么样了？
How's your master,Boleyn?
是洛克福特勋爵 潘宁顿
that's Lord Rochford to you,Pennington.
请称我为威廉·潘宁顿爵士 索思韦尔
Sir William Pennington to you,Southwell.
你主人最近怎么样
and how is your master?
操他的布兰顿先生
Master fucking Brandon?
他是不是还非得用那种最恶毒
Does he still persist in using the most foul
最侮辱性的语言诋毁我主人的女儿 安妮女士？
And abusive language against my master's daughter,Lady Anne,
- 她马上要做王后了 - 请你自己去问公爵
- Who is soon to be Queen? - The Duke can speak for himself.
- 我在问你呢 潘宁顿 - 公爵不愿意
- I'm asking you,Pennington! - His Grace wants nothing to do
与国王的娼妓成为王后一事有任何关系
With the elevation of the King's whore!
谁是妓女？
Who's a whore?
- 让我过去 - 先过了我这一关
- Let me pass! - Not till you've paid for that.
快跑 去找公爵 快去
Run! Fetch the Duke! Go!
神父 我想在这里寻求避难
Father,I seek sanctuary in this place.
当然可以 我的孩子
Of course,my child.
收起你们的剑 先生们 这是上帝的领地
Put up your swords,gentlemen. This is a place of God.
- 拔剑自卫啊 潘宁顿 - 主啊
- Defend yourself, Pennington. - Dear God!
你在这动武不仅侮辱了你服侍的波林家族
You dishonour the Boleyn family whom you serve.
同时也冒犯了上帝
And you offend God by offering violence here.
住手 看在上帝的份上 够了
Stop now,for the love of God! Enough is enough!
你这个笨蛋 理查德 你把他杀了
You fool,Richard. You've killed him!
大人 他们把他杀了
Oh,my Lord. They've killed him.
杀人凶手
Murderers!
我的大人 大人 我向你祈求 以主的名义
Oh my Lord,my Lord,i beg you,in the name of our Lord.
这里已经发生了一起凶杀
One murder has been committed here already.
- 人渣 - 公爵大人 我们…
- You scum. - Your Grace,we...
闭嘴 你们两个该死的
Shut up! You're both dead men.
大人 我求求你了
My Lord,listen! I beg you.
在教堂里行凶的人
Those who commit murder in Church
会被上帝诅咒
are damned in the eyes of God.
都是你干的好事 波林
This is your doing,Boleyn!
安妮女士不希望受到打扰
Lady Anne is not to be disturbed.
一夜之间所有人都希望跟安妮女士扯上关系
Suddenly everyone is beating a path to Lady Anne's door!
你怎么看 怀特先生
Why do you suppose that is, Mr. Wyatt?
因为比起落日 人们更喜欢朝阳
Because everyone prefers a rising sun to a setting sun,
斯米顿先生
Mr. Smeaton.
说说看 最近你在写什么呢
Now tell me,what are you writing at the moment?
一首讽刺诗
A satire.
你觉得这些事很可笑？
You find all this funny?
所有严肃的事情 都有可笑的一面
Well,it has its funny side, like all serious things.
举个例 你肯定觉得好笑 马克
For example-and this will make you laugh,Mark
我刚刚接到克伦威尔先生的通知
Mr. Cromwell just told me
我已被任命为枢密院成员
I've been appointed to the Privy Council.
太荒谬了
That's ridiculous.
生活本身就是荒谬的
Everything in life is ridiculous.
从另一个方面看
And to suppose otherwise is...
这只是人性的虚荣
It's human vanity.
- 怀特先生 - 夫人
- Mr. Wyatt. - My Lady.
- 你猜怎么着？- 不 猜不到
- You know what? - No,i don't.
我最近忽然非常想吃苹果
I have a furious hankering for apples,
好像我以前从未吃过似的 都三天了
Such as I've never had before. It started three days ago.
- 苹果？- 是的 苹果
- Apples? - Yes! apples.
国王说这是我怀孕的征兆
The King told me it was a sign I was pregnant.
可是我说才不是呢
But I said it was nothing of the sort.
这是什么意思？
What was that about?
法国那边有什么好消息？
What news from France?
没什么能令陛下满意的消息
none to give Your Majesty any satisfaction.
虽然法国国王答应代表陛下
Although he promised to make representations to the Pope
在教皇面前陈情
On Your Majesty's behalf
可是实际上他没有
King Francis did no such thing.
没关系
It doesn't matter.
我们还能指望法国国王怎样呢
What else should we have expected from the King of France?
事实上 现在我反而有了很好的理由…
The fact is,I now have a good reason...
一个非常好的理由 不用再等教皇的决定了
A very good reason,not to wait for the Pope's decision.
必须立即公布我废除婚约的消息
The annulment of my marriage must be declared immediately.
陛下现在已经是教会的领袖了
Well,as Your Majesty is head of the Church now,
- 您自己就可以… - 不
- You yourself could... - no.
婚约取消仍然需要得到教会方面的同意
The annulment should still be decided and
并应该由教会正式宣布
declared by the Church proper.
也就是说 坎特伯雷大主教
That is to say, the Archbishop of Canterbury.
陛下也知道 这个职位一直是空缺的
as Your Majesty knows, there remains a vacancy for that position.
我心中已经有了满意的人选
I think I know exactly who will suit.
克朗默先生
Mr. Cranmer!
- 什么事 - 您从德国运来的东西
- Yes. - Your belongings from Germany.
谢谢
Thank you. uh...
你能不能… 谢谢你 先生 终于到了
If you could just... thank you,sir. At last.
凯瑟琳娜
Katharina.
好了
It's over now.
你终于到了
You're here.
托马斯 见到你终于松了口气
I'm very relieved to see you,Thomas.
我还以为我会死呢
I thought I was going to die!
即使是非法妻子 这样旅行也真够呛
It's not the nicest way to travel,even for an illegal wife!
都结束了
It's over now.
你现在到了
You're here now.
肯原谅我吗？
Do you forgive me?
这… 这里就是英格兰了？
so... this is England?
这里就是英格兰了
This is England.
他们想任命克朗默先生为大主教
They want to make Cranmer Archbishop.
我很好奇教皇是不是清楚克朗默在这的声誉
I wonder if the Pope knows of the reputation Cranmer has here
他全心全意为路德派运动尽力
For being devoted heart and soul to the Lutheran movement.
他曾经是波林家族的专任牧师
he was once chaplain to the Boleyns.
应该要求他特别宣誓
He ought to be required to take a special oath
- 决不干涉离婚的事情 - 他当然会干涉
- Not to meddle with the divorce. - Of course he'll meddle!
这才是他们的真正用意
That's what they want!
他们才不在乎神圣教会
They don't care about Holy Church anymore.
甚至已经不在乎人民
They don't even care about the people.
国王已被蒙蔽 除了上帝他无所畏惧
The King, in his blindness, fears no one but God.
我担心王后
I fear for the Queen.
据说安妮·波林公开表示讨厌王后和公主
They say Anne Boleyn hates her openly and her daughter,too.
她曾经恐吓过公主
She's made threats against the child.
说这话时谨慎一点
those are dangerous words.
也为你自己孩子们的性命着想一下
Think also of the lives of your own children.
这是什么？
What is this?
反土著奴役教皇敕令 圣父
The Bull Sublimus Dei,Holy Father.
提示我一下
Remind me.
废除奴役制度的提案
It forbids the enslavement
解放新大陆地区的本地人
Of the native peoples of the new world.
这我们非常乐意签署
Then we sign it very willingly.
因为事实上 坎佩基奥
For the fact is,Campeggio
欧洲国王们有权无德
that the Kings of europe have power but no morality.
我必须主持公道
I must act as their conscience.
他们是我任性的孩子 我作为他们的父亲
They are my wilful children and I their father,
要带领他们走向正义的道路
Leading them along the paths of righteousness.
愿主庇佑
So help me God.
- 这个呢？- 英格兰国王申请
- And this? - the King of England asks your approval
任命新的坎特伯雷大主教
To appoint a new Archbishop of Canterbury,
接任已经去世的渥兰大主教
After the death of Archbishop Warham.
人们还说他不在乎呢
and people say he doesn't care!
候选人叫什么？
What is the name of the candidate?
托马斯·克朗默
Thomas Cranmer.
我们对这克朗默有何了解？
What do we know of this Cranmer?
知之甚少 他只是位小牧师 无名小卒
Virtually nothing. He's an obscure cleric. A nobody.
很多传言说他私底下信奉路德教
There are strong rumors that he is a secret Lutheran.
那我们便不能批准他的任命
Then we should not approve his appointment.
不能 我也这么想 教皇陛下
No. Not in my opinion,Holiness.
不过…
And yet...
我们得给英国教会一个机会
We want to give the English Church the opportunity
使其恢复对真正信仰的原有忠诚
To return to its first allegiance,and our true faith.
我们得取悦国王
We want to please the King.
我们得让他对我们感恩戴德
We want to make him beholden to us.
有什么能比
What better way to please him
无名小卒的任命更令他高兴呢？再说
Than to approve the appointment of a nobody? After all,
一个无名之辈又能对教廷有什么威胁呢？
What harm can a nobody inflict upon our Holy Church?
大人
Your Grace.
很高兴看到你被批准接任大主教
We are most pleased to see you confirmed as Archbishop.
陛下 我承认对于接任此职
Your Majesty,I confess I had some scruples
我还有所顾虑
About accepting the office,
因为我必须得到教皇的恩准
Since I must receive it at the Pope's hand.
你不必对罗马教廷尽忠
You are not beholden to Rome.
只需向上帝和我尽责
Only to God,and me.
现在 大主教
And now,Archbishop,
作为本国神权管辖的首席大臣
as principle minister of spiritual jurisdiction in our realm,
我要你立即为我的要事做一劳永逸的了断
I ask you to determine once and for all,my Great Matter.
我的第一次婚姻是否有效？
Whether or not my first marriage was valid.
陛下 我将立刻着手办理此事
Majesty,I shall address the question with the greatest urgency,
尽快宣判我的裁定
And presently pronounce my verdict.
- 克伦威尔先生 - 陛下？
- Mr. Cromwell. - Majesty?
托马斯·莫尔已经离去
Since the departure of Thomas More,
英格兰正缺一位大法官
England has lacked a Chancellor.
- 我相信你能担此重任 - 谢陛下
- I am trusting you to fill that office. - Majesty.
他在哪？沙福克在哪？
Where is he? Where's Suffolk?
在万能的主的面前 我们在此集结
We are gathered here together,in the sight of God almighty,
见证他和她的神圣婚姻
To join in Holy matrimony,this man and this woman.
请你们彼此宣誓
And will you both answer that
你们从此正当结合
you will keep all these coming days rightful,
明智而慎重
With right wiseness and discretion,
仁慈而互信
With mercy and truth.
愿吾主保佑
So help you God.
布里列顿阁下
Master Breredon.
没用的 我失败了
It's no use. I failed.
而且我再也无法忍受此地
And I can no longer bear this place.
那就去你内心向往之地
Then go where your heart tells you.
带着吾主的保佑
With God's blessing.
莫尔宫
The More
夫人 沙福克公爵觐见
My Lady, Duke of Surffolk
大人
Your Grace.
夫人…
My Lady...
我奉王命至此
His Majesty has ordered me here.
陛下命我知会您…
He's asked me to tell you...
他警告您别不必妄图再回到他身边…
He warns you not to try to return to him...
他现在已与安妮女士完婚
Since he is now married to the Lady Anne.
从今往后 您将禁用王后之名
From henceforth,you must abstain from using the title of Queen.
头衔改为威尔士亲王太妃
You will now be referred to as the Princess Dowager of Wales.
您必须减小日常开支
You must also cut your household expenses.
出于慷慨 陛下允许您继续享有您的财产
In his generosity,the King allows you to keep your property,
但将不再继续支付仆人费用
But will no longer pay your servants' wages,
及日常开支
Or your household expenses.
那我的女儿呢？
And what of my daughter?
- 玛丽呢？我能见她吗？- 夫人
- What of Mary? May I see her? - Madam.
宽恕我
Forgive me.
你知道吗 布兰顿先生？
You know something, Mr. Bradon?
如果我必须在极喜
If I had to choose between extreme happiness
与极悲之间做出选择…
And extreme sorrow...
我总会选择悲伤
I would always choose sorrow.
因为当你快乐时 你会忘记…
For when you are happy you forget...
忘记信仰 忘记上帝
You forget about spiritual things; you forget about God.
但当你悲伤时…
But in your sorrow...
上帝总与你同在
He is always with you.
愿吾主保佑 并与你同在 夫人
May Lord bless you and keep you,my Lady.
只要我一息尚存
As long as I live,
我会永远称我为英格兰王后
I will call myself the Queen of England.
- 感谢上帝 - 阿门
- Deo gracias. - Amen.
大人 我有些消息
Your Grace,I have some news.
我得知克伦威尔先生将向议会
I have learned that Mr. Cromwell is to present
提交另一份议案
another bill to parliament.
关于上诉限制的议案
The Act of Restraint of Appeals.
在这看似无害的题目下
And under its innocuous title
隐藏着极为反动的意图
Does it conceal its most revolutionary intent.
怎么写的？
What does it say?
"英格兰领土作为一个帝国"
"This realm of England is an Empire,
"为教会最高领袖及国王所治"
"governed by one supreme head and King,
"只向上帝尽忠"
"And owing no allegiance except to God."
以后 事关精神领域的所有最终上诉
In future,all final appeals on spiritual matters will be heard,
均非到罗马 而止于英格兰
Not in rome,but in England,
即国王现在享有…
Where the King will now enjoy...
"绝对 全然 而且至高的"
"plenary,whole and entire power,pre-Eminence"
"权威 享有君主特权及裁决权"
"authority,prerogative and jurisdiction."
我想那意味着
Which means,I take it,
法案阻止了
That the act prohibits the hearing of
教皇对国王企图使婚姻无效申诉的裁决权
the King's nullity suit by the Pope.
同时也挡住了王后
And,by the same token,bars the Queen
向梵蒂冈对此申诉裁决结果的反诉
From appealing to the Vatican against any decision made here.
所言极是
Exactly.
从未有任何英格兰国王被授予如此绝对权势
No English sovereign has ever been granted such absolute power.
- 可怜的凯瑟琳 - 更糟糕的
- Poor Catherine. - It's worse.
- 是传说国王已与安妮女士秘密完婚 - 不
- There are rumours that the King has married Anne in secret. - No!
而且她已经有孕在身
and that she is already with child.
诸位殿下
Your Eminences.
作为此次合理程序组建的教会法庭结果
At the conclusion of this properly constituted ecclesiastical court,
我将宣布经由我们一致同意的裁决
I am ready to pronounce the verdict agreed by us all.
很遗憾有些人不愿到场见证此刻
It is a pity that certain persons refused to come here and testify!
但这绝影响不到我们的裁决
But that in itself holds no bearing upon our conclusions.
裁决是 宣布英格兰王亨利
Which are that the union between King Henry of England.
与阿拉贡的凯瑟琳的婚姻无效
And Katherine of Aragon is declared null and void.
因此 国王与安妮·波林的婚姻
And therefore,that the King's marriage to Anne Boleyn
宣布合法有效
Is declared both valid and lawful,
上帝为证
In the eyes of God.
先生
Sir.
- 伊丽莎白？- 别这样
- Elizabeth? - Not that.
那该怎样？
Then what?
虽未经本人允许 我代表我的女主人来此
I came on behalf of my Lady,though not with her permission.
托马斯 她正遭受着极大的不幸…
Thomas,she is in a most wretched way...
被遗弃 遭背叛
Abandoned and betrayed.
国王用尽手段羞辱她
It seems so cruel of the King
实在残酷之极
To humiliate her in every way,
他居然迎娶了那个婊子…
Pretending to marry that harlot...
- 什么？- 你还没听说吗
- What? - Did you not know?
沙福克公爵奉命来通知她
The Duke of Suffolk came to tell her
国王已经完婚…
That the King has married...
安妮… 波林？
Anne...Boleyn?
但与我何干？
But what can I do about any of that?
现在你是枢密院委员
You are now a Privy Councillor.
还是克伦威尔先生的座上宾
And a client of Mr. Cromwell.
我想你可为我的女主人进言求情
I thought you could speak up for my Mistress.
克伦威尔先生是最最不可能
Mr. Cromwell is the least likely man
同情你家女主人的 伊丽莎白 你该知道
To sympathise with your Mistress. You must know that,Elizabeth.
那你呢？
But what about you?
你要是还对我有点情谊
If you still have feelings for me,
你就该为她说句话
You will speak out for her.
只好抱歉了
I'm sorry.
作为圣彼得的继承人
As the successor of St. Peter,
我庄严地谴责
I do solemnly condemn the separation
英格兰国王和阿拉贡的凯瑟琳的离异
Of the King of England from Katherine of Aragon,
对于他之后的秘密婚姻
And his subsequent secret marriage,
我宣布无效
Which I declare null and void.
兹一事体 关乎国王陛下
This matter,of the validity
婚姻是否有效
Of His Majesty's marriage,
只能由元老院裁决
Can only be decided by the Curia,
而元老院至今还未下定论
Which has not yet reached its conclusion.
我给国王在九月之前
I will give the King until september
请回自己的前妻的期限
To take back his former wife...
否则 将会被逐出教会
On pain of excommunication,
从此脱离神圣教会
Which is separation from Holy Church,
与教团分离
From communion,
与上帝分离
And from God.
谢谢 诸位殿下
Thank you,Your Excellencies.
请向你们的主人转达我的话 无论何地
You may communicate my words to your masters everywhere.
跟我来 布里列顿阁下
Come with me,Master Brereton.
圣父
Holy Father,
这就是我向您提及的年轻英格兰绅士
This is the young English gentleman I was telling you about,
他为我们带来了英格兰宫廷的消息
Who brought us the news from the English Court.
- 威廉·布里列顿阁下 - 我的孩子
- Master William Brereton. - My son.
我们对你
We are grateful to you
为我们带来这些不幸的消息
For bringing news of these terrible events
并尽力阻止它们的发生表示感谢
And for all you tried to do to prevent them.
我试图为您把她除掉
I tried to rid you of her,
但不幸的是 圣父 我失败了
But unfortunately,Holy father,I failed.
谁知道呢 我的孩子？
Who knows,my son?
上帝自有其神秘之道
God works in mysterious ways.
红衣主教坎佩基奥告诉我说
Cardinal Campeggio tells me
你打算留在罗马而不回英格兰
You want to stay in Rome now, and not return to England.
是这样吗？
Is that correct?
是的 圣父
Yes,Holy father.
我更愿意和众多有信仰的人在一起
I would rather remain with the flock of the faithful.
布里顿先生 最近
Recently,Master Brereton,
我颁布了一份新的神圣的教令
I have ordained a new and very special Holy order.
他们是教会军队
They are the militantis ecclesiae
基督的卫士
The Soldiers of Christ.
他们被称作耶稣会信徒
These Jesuits, as they are called,
这些卫士将要走至那些人人畏惧的地方
These soldiers,will go where others fear,
那些充满危险的地方
Where often they will meet great danger,
为传播天主教的信仰 传达上帝的旨意
In order to promote the catholic faith and take the word of God
带给那些异教徒
To heathens and heretics.
我看得出你对此事业充满着热情
I see already your passion for this cause,
我恳请你
And I beg you,
加入这个教令
Join the order,
加入反抗异教徒的十字军团
Join the crusade against heresy,
然后重回英格兰
And return to England,
甚至冒着以身殉难的危险
Even at the risk of martyrdom.
- 克伦威尔先生 - 陛下有何吩咐？
- Mr. Cromwell. - Majesty?
加冕礼准备得如何？
How are the preparations for the coronation?
一切顺利 陛下
They're going well, Majesty.
我希望我的人民能爱戴他们的新王后
I want the people to love their new Queen
正如我一样
as I love her.
如果我能爱她
And if I can love her,
他们为何不能呢？
Why shouldn't they?
我想他们会爱戴新王后的
I assure Your Majesty they will love her,
他们没有理由不这么做
And shall have every reason to do so.
是的 我喜欢
Yes,I like it.
侯爵夫人
Madame La Marquise.
不 是妹妹
No. Just sister.
你怎么样 我的妹妹？
How are you,sister?
你们俩都好吗
How are both of you?
我们都很好
We are both very well.
听我说 陛下和我去拜访了一位有名的占星家
Listen. the King and I have visited a famous astrologer,
他证实了医师的说法
Who confirmed what the physicians say,
我打心底就知道 是个男孩
And what I know in my Heart. That it's a boy.
陛下高兴坏了
The King is overjoyed.
他见人就想说 可被我阻止了
He keeps wanting to tell people, but I tell him not to.
至少现在别说
Not yet anyway.
来看看这些
Come and look at these.
荷尔拜因先生设计了各种
Mr. Holbein has been designing all kinds of things
- 加冕礼上要用的东西 - 太漂亮了
- For the coronation procession. - They're so beautiful.
荷尔拜因先生简直是个天才
Mr. Holbein is indeed a genius.
你害怕了吗？
Are you scared?
安妮 你在怕什么？
Anne? What is it?
没什么 只是…
Oh,it's nothing. It's...
怎么了 相公？
What's wrong,husband?
我要为国王和她的婊子护驾
I'm going to have to attend on the King and that bitch of his
在那婊子的加冕礼上
at her coronation.
渥西怎么叫她的来着
What did Wolsey used to call her?
黑乌鸦
The black crow!
- 你能不能装点小病？- 我本来可以的…
- Can you not plead some indisposition? - I could...
即使国王已封我为届时的王室内务总管
Even though the King has made me High Constable for the day.
但如果我这么做了 陛下一定会要了我的脑袋
But if I did, His Majesty would remove my head,
那我就真的"病"了
And then I should be genuinely indisposed.
好吧 那就好好保护你的脑袋
Very well. So keep your head.
不管怎么说 它都是个漂亮的脑袋
It's a pretty head, in any case,
我可不想失去它
And I don't want to lose it either.
但是收起你的认知和怒意
But store up your knowledge and your anger.
切忌鲁莽从事 这总是不好的
Don't act impulsively. it's always a mistake.
直到有一天 当其他人也想这么做的时候
But one day,with others so disposed,
再把它们释放
use them both,
如果可以的话
And if you can,
把她拉下台 彻底地毁灭她
Bring her down and destroy her.
注意了 注意了
Hear ye,hear ye!
为我们的陛下
Make way for His Gracious Majesty,
亨利国王和安妮·波林女士
King Henry,and the Lady Anne Boleyn,
彭布罗克女侯爵让路
Marquess of Pembroke!
让路 让路
Make way! Make way!
人群呢？
Where are the crowds?
人都哪儿去了？
Where are the people?
- 这儿发生了什么事？- 他死了
- What the hell happened here? - He's dead!
- 被射杀的 - 我的上帝
- Shot! - My God!
继续前进
Keep the procession moving.
不行
I can't!
- 刚怎么了？- 一场意外
- What was that? - An accident.
陛下您完全无须担心
Nothing for Your Majesty to be concerned about.
没有什么能破坏今天的活动
For nothing on earth is going to spoil this day.
恳求造物圣灵
Veni, Creator Spiritus
降临我们身边
Mentus tuorum visita.
以你圣宠神恩
Imple superna gratia
充满你所造者之心
Quae tu creasti pectora.
经由你的指引
Tu septiformis munere,
把圣父带来我们身边
Digitus paternae dexterae;
我们一直坚信着
Tu rite promissum patris,
这是你的指引
Sermone ditans guttura.
启发我们的认知
Accende lumen sensibus,
把爱满溢我们心中
Infunde amorem cordibus,
减少我们身体的渴望
Infirma nostri corporis,
坚守我们的美德 阿门
Virtute firmans perpeti. Amen.
等一下
Wait!
把它给我
Give it to me.
以圣·爱德华的王冠
With this, St Edward's crown.
我庄严地为你加冕
I do solemnly crown you
英格兰的王后
Queen of England.
这里…
And here...
是两柄元首的权杖
Are the two sceptres of the sovereign.
愿荣誉与高贵永随我们的安妮王后
Honour and Grace be to our Queen Anne.
祝愿你凡事顺利
May you prosper,go forward,
祝愿你能怀有国王的新王子
And may you bear a new son of the King's blood.
那是一次企图暗杀行动
That was an assassination attempt,
不是针对你的就是针对王后的
Either upon you or upon the Queen.
- 一个男仆被杀了 - 谢谢 克伦威尔先生
- A groom was killed. - Thank you, Mr. Cromwell.
甜心 怎么样？
Sweetheart. How was that?
你喜欢这个城市吗？有没有什么不称心的？
Did you like the city? Was not everything well done?
是的 太美丽了
Yes,it was beautiful.
就是人太少了
But so few people!
他们没有脱帽致敬 也没有人欢呼
And they kept their hats on their heads. And no one shouted.
比起游行我觉得更像一个葬礼
It was more like a funeral than a parade.
你还有一个晚会要参加
You have a party to go to.
我希望你高兴
I want you to be happy.
希望你能有微笑
I want you to smile.
记住 你现在是我的王后了
Remember, you are my Queen now.
我知道
I know.
- 但是… - 但是我说了 你是我的王后
- But.. - But I said, you are my Queen.
所有人都在等你
Everyone is waiting for you.
我怎么没看到费施尔主教
I don't see Bishop Fisher here.
他不在 陛下
No,Your Majesty.
那托马斯·莫尔爵士呢？
And where is Sir Thomas more?
我也没看到他
I don't see him here either.
没有邀请他吗？
Was he not invited?
肯定邀请他了 陛下
He was most certainly invited, Your Majesty.
那就是他自己不想来
Then he chose not to attend.
饿了吗 女士们
Hungry,ladies?
大人
Your Grace.
既然你被任命为今天的王室内务总管
Since you were appointed High Constable today,
游行中发生的事故
What happened in the procession
就是你的责任 我要知道是谁开的枪
Was your fault. I want to know who fired that shot.
我已经竭尽全力去调查了 勋爵
I am already endeavouring to find out,my Lord.
我当然相信你 大人
Oh,I sincerely trust that you are, Your Grace.
我还没有忘记潘宁顿
I have not for gotten Pennington.
因为我认为那是你的错
For I feel that was your fault.
为波林干杯
Cheers to the Boleyns.
The Boleyns!
英格兰的新王后
And England's new Queen!
玛莉 这是为我放的礼花
Oh,Mary! And it's all for me!
加冕礼怎么样
How was the coronation?
冷清 乏味
It was a cold,meagre
让人很不舒服
And uncomfortable thing.
你的缺席很引人注目 托马斯爵士
And your absence was noted, Sir Thomas.
王后陛下对于这些怎么看待？
How is Her Majesty bearing up under all this?
我不允许见她了
I am no longer allowed to see her.
我们之前互通书信也日益艰难
And it is increasingly difficult for us to exchange letters.
我去试试看
I'm going to try and see her.
这么做很危险 连表达赞美之辞
That would be so dangerous. Even to speak a word
都有入狱的危险
In her praise is to risk imprisonment.
我还是要尽力争取
Nevertheless.
回顾过往
I have been thinking about the past,
我坚信国王有朝一日
When I believed the King to be
会成为天主教国家的贤明君主
The most enlightened and promising prince in Christendom.
我认定他会将英格兰带入全盛时期
I was sure his reign would be a Golden Age.
我曾寄予厚望…
I had such high hopes...
费施尔主教已被软禁
Bishop Fisher has been placed under house arrest.
你要多加小心 尤斯塔斯大使
You should beware yourself, Eustace.
你们行事务必令世人可敬 谨慎
You will all be honourable,discreet,
公正 廉洁
Just and thrifty in your conduct.
你们将向世人传达神的旨意
You will present a Godly spectacle to others,
每日出席弥撒
Attend mass daily
行为举止应彰显高尚品德的风范
And display a virtuous demeanour.
违者立即以免职及放逐论处
On pain of instant dismissal and banishment,
禁止争斗
You must not quarrel,
诅咒 或发表邪恶猥亵之言论
Swear... or say evil and lewd things.
做出下流之行为
Nor ever behave lewdly.
你们将为世人树立典范
You will set a standard for everyone else.
都明白了吗
Do you understand?
是 陛下
Yes,Your Majesty.
禁止出入妓院
And you don't go to brothels.
我会在这里放一本
I will keep here a copy
丁道尔所译的英文圣经
Of Tyndale's english bible.
你们可以自由翻阅
All of you are free to read it,
从中汲取其精髓
And draw spiritual nourishment from it...
旧时代已经过去
For the old days are gone.
如今一切皆已改变
Everything is changed now.
承蒙国王陛下圣恩 各位有幸
Thanks to His Majesty, you have all been delivered
挣脱教皇的奴役和黑暗统治
From the darkness and bondage of papal thraldom,
破除崇拜和迷信
Idolatry and superstition.
对我
This is a new beginning. For me.
对你们
For you.
对英格兰都是崭新的开始
And for England.
勒德洛城堡 威尔士边界
Ludlow Castle. The Welsh Marches
大人
Sir.
玛莉小姐
Lady Mary,
我来此通知你坎特伯雷大主教
I have come to inform you of the judgements made recently
近期做出的裁决
By His Grace,the Archbishop of Canterbury.
国王陛下与你母亲的婚姻
His Majesty's marriage to your mother
被宣判无效
Has been declared null and void.
你母亲不再是合法的英格兰王后
Your mother was never legally Queen of England,
必须接受亲王太妃头衔
And must now accept the title of Dowager Princess.
你也不能再自称为公主
Just as you have no longer the right to call yourself princess,
从今往后 头衔改为玛莉小姐
But from now on must be known to all as Lady Mary.
与此同时
At the same time,
国王陛下与安妮王后成婚
His Majesty's recent marriage to Queen Anne
已被宣布合法有效
Has been declared legal and valid.
她的加冕礼已在上周举行
Her coronation took place in london this past week.
除我母亲之外 我不知道还有其他英格兰王后
I know of no Queen of England save my mother.
而且我也不会承认其他人的王后资格
And I will accept no other Queen,except my mother.
这样的话
In which case,
我不得不禁止你与你母亲通信
I have to tell you that you are forbidden to communicate
即日起开始执行
In any way with your mother, from this day forward.
我能给她写信吗
may I not even write to her?
一张道别短笺都不可以
not even a farewell note,
考虑到你…
Considering your...
不妥协的态度
Intransigence.
托马斯·莫尔爵士觐见 夫人
Sir Thomas more, my Lady.
托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas.
陛下
Your Majesty.
请原谅我如此接见你
Forgive me for receiving you like this,
我身体不适
But I do not feel well.
您所遭受的一切
What you suffer is known.
世人皆知
To a great many people, both here and abroad.
此事是不公正的
As is the injustice of it,
您却以宽厚仁慈之心对待
As well as the grace with which you endure it.
如今
now it seems...
我不能再自称王后了…
I must cease to call myself Queen...
即使我受过加冕礼
Even though I was crowned so, and anointed.
他们说如果我拒绝
They say that if I refuse,
国王将不再承认我的女儿
The King will withdraw his fatherly love for my daughter.
我不会屈服
I shall not yield,
既不是为了我女儿
Neither for my daughter's sake
也不是为了其他人
Or anyone else's.
即使千人之死 我都不会允许自己去谴责
Not for a thousand deaths would I consent to damn my soul,
我或是我国王丈夫的灵魂
Or that of my husband the King.
请再次原谅 托马斯爵士
Please forgive me again, Sir Thomas.
我已经不再习惯接见访客了
I am not very used to visitors any more.
大部分人都会被拦下
They are mostly forbidden me.
你怎么得到许可令的
How did you get permission?
我亲自联系了克伦威尔先生
I wrote to Mr. Cromwell personally.
你是个勇士
Then you are a brave man.
我不这么做就是懦夫
I'd be a coward to do otherwise.
我无法假装对此事
I cannot pretend to be detached
漠不关心
From these events.
我一直力促
I have been encouraging
国会和其他地方的支持者
your supporters in parliament, and elsewhere,
表明他们的立场
To speak their minds
支持您
And stand up for you.
谢谢
Thank you,
- 托马斯爵士 谢谢 - 陛下
- Sir Thomas. Thank you. - Majesty.
安妮…
Anne...
亲爱的
Sweetheart.
我不能 现在不行
I can't. Not now.
等孩子出生…
While the baby...
她很优雅 不是吗
Exquisite,isn't she?
埃莉诺·鲁克女士
Lady Eleanor Luke.
她的家族在牛津郡拥有地产
Her family has an estate in Oxfordshire.
需要我代表你和她谈谈吗
Shall I talk to her on your behalf?
宫庭生活如何 马克
How do you like life at court,Mark?
我觉得
I feel...
- 我感觉幸运至极 大人 - 至极？
- I feel twice fortunate,my Lord. - Twice?
允许我前往此地已是幸事
Once for being allowed to come here,
而得到您家族的资助则幸运至极
And twice for the patronage of your family.
我们乐于资助艺术家
We like to patronize artists.
有才华的人 画家荷尔拜因在我家暂住
Men of talent. The painter Holbein stayed with us,
舍妹支援了众多音乐家和唱诗班
And my sister supports many musicians and choirs.
是的 那么令妹是非常
Yes,well,your sister is quite
有才华的音乐家了
A talented musician herself...
也是个非常年轻漂亮的女人
As well as a very beautiful young woman.
即使这样…
Even though...
即使这样？
Even though...?
还是没有他哥哥完美
Not as beautiful as her brother.
这是什么
What's this?
罗马元老院的最终决议
The final decision of the curia in Rome.
他们作出了对凯瑟琳有利的判决
They have found for Katherine.
宣布我这次婚姻无效
They declare my new marriage invalid,
任何婚生子女
and any children produced from it,
都属私生子
Illegitimate.
如果我不悔改重归凯瑟琳
The Pope threatens to excommunicate me
教皇威胁要将我逐出教会
If I do not return to Katherine.
太晚了
He's too late.
坚持住 坚持住
Hold on. Hold on.
坚持住 勇敢极了
Shh. Hold on. How brave!
就要出来了
Here it comes.
我要你安排比武 宴会 假面舞会
And I want you to organize jousts,banquets and masques.
庆祝我儿子的诞生
To celebrate the birth of my son.
我还没有决定叫他亨利还是爱德华
I can't decide whether to call him Henry or Edward.
我已经邀请法国大使
And I've already asked the French ambassador to
在洗礼仪式上托住他
hold him at the font during his Christening.
如有任何闪失 那就开战
If he drops him,it's war.
就是现在 安妮 就是现在 用力推
It's here,Anne, it's here! Push!
推 推
Push! push!
- 是什么 怎么回事 - 没事没事
- What is it? what's happened? - Nothing! Nothing!
陛下产下了非常健康的女婴
Your Majesty has given birth to a very healthy baby girl.
你对此事不觉得震惊吗 殿下
And did you not find such occurrences shocking,Eminency?
陛下 我是威尼斯人
Your Majesty, I am a Venetian.
我来自
I come from a city
充斥着赌徒和娼妓的城市
where all the men are gamblers and all the women whores.
这也就不足为奇了
What is there to be shocked about,huh?
陛下
Majesty.
我非常抱歉
I'm so sorry.
我们都还年轻
You and I are both young,
有主的庇佑 会生下儿子的
And by God's Grace, boys will follow.
- 埃莉诺女士 - 陛下
- Lady Eleanor. - Your Majesty.
你会下棋吗
Do you play chess?
会的 陛下
Yes,Your Majesty.
过来 我们开始吧
Come,let's play.
我第一步走这里
That's my first move.